Genevieve LaLonde

.linkedin.com/in/genevieve-lalonde/ • coding-gen.github.io/

Portland, OR

My passion for languages and computer science has drawn me to research Natural Language Processing as part of my masters in computer science at Portland State University. I am one term away from graduating, with a GPA of 3.85. I also bring an abundance of work experience with modern distributed cloud SQL databases from my half decade working at SingleStore, as well as performance monitoring and optimization at SingleStore and at New Relic. For my BA I studied languages and computer science, and speak 4 languages. I am a tenacious puzzle solver who quickly picks up new concepts and enjoys mentoring and training my teammates.

Employment



Portland State University. Portland, OR.

Mar 2022 - June 2022

Data Engineering Teaching Assistant

- Assisted teaching in class, including advising students on their code.
- Design and update course content around data mining, cleaning, and storage.
- Host the course Diango web server, serving simulated "realtime" data.



SingleStore (formerly MemSQL). Remote, Portland, OR. Sept 2017 - Mar 2022

Performance Benchmarking Engineer. Jun 2021 - Mar 2022

- Maintain and expand custom python benchmarking framework.
 - Taught myself the python code.
 - Create benchmarks from customer use cases, fix bugs.
 - Run regression tests on TPC and custom benchmarks.
 - Compare SingleStore performance to our competitors.
 - Upgrade system to new AWS infrastructure.
- Serve as Subject Matter Expert for Support, Sales Engineering, Documentation, and Training teams. See award: SELECT *

Database Performance Engineer. Nov 2020 - Jun 2021

- Serve as the escalation point for query tuning type customer requests.
- Mentoring, hiring, training, and documentation.
- I created this role. See award: Growth and Learning.

Senior Support Engineer. Apr 2019 - Nov 2020

- Resolved advanced technical customer requests, including query tuning, python transforms in ETL pipelines, internal database memory usage, etc.
- Internal technical trainer for the whole Customer Success department.

Support Engineer. Sept 2017 - Apr 2019

Advise customers on distributed database management and configuration.



New Relic. Portland, OR.

Mar 2016 - Sept 2017

Technical Support Engineer II and Team Lead

- Performance monitoring of linux servers, and PHP/Golang web applications.
- Created a regex training 1 month after hire that became integral onboarding.

Human Languages

- Native language: English
- Excellent proficiency in: German, Spanish, French.
- Beginner in: Japanese, Wolof

Genevieve LaLonde

.linkedin.com/in/genevieve-lalonde/ • coding-gen.github.io/

Portland, OR

Education



Portland State University. Portland, OR.

Graduating June 2023

Master of Science in Computer Science. GPA: 3.85

Area of focus: natural language processing (NLP) and machine learning.

Research: how multilingual models improve performance in low-resource languages



University of Washington Online. Seattle, WA. Computational linguistics.

July 2014 - Dec 2015



Albert Ludwigs Universität Freiburg. Freiburg, Germany. Oct 2013 – Aug 2014 Studied Computer Science in German to develop a technical vocabulary in German.



Lewis & Clark College. Portland, OR.

Aug 2005 – May 2009

Bachelor of Arts in Foreign Languages, minor in Computer Science. GPA 3.3

Awards



SELECT * **Award**. SingleStore

Dec 2021

Empowered the Sales Engineering team by creating and delivering a query tuning training on tooling and metrics, live database schema redesign, and review of customer query plans.



Best Overall Presentation and 1st Place in Extended Features

Jun 2021

Data Engineering course at Portland State University

For the quality of my final project presentation and my pipeline's extra features, including logging, data backup, cold storage, and an insert-only-once guarantee.



Mem-tality Award for Growth and Learning. SingleStore

Sept 2020

Enabled SingleStore to offer query tuning services, by teaching myself query optimization.



Sales MVP. NewRelic

Apr 2017

Delivered exemplary customer support at a critical time to close an important deal.

Memberships



Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)

2022-2023

Conferences

Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)

2022

PyCon

2023

Technical Skills

- NLP: pretrained language models, finetuning, multilingual models, chatGPT, text preprocessing, model training, evaluation, visualizations, python for NLP (NLTK, SpaCY, NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, SciPy, Matplotlib, PyTorch, PyAudio, etc.)
- Programming: Python, Rust, Linux CLI, Bash scripting, Node.js, HTML, CSS, Regex
- Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, SingleStore, MariaDB, Spark, Cloud Datastore, DynamoDB, query optimization, TPC benchmarks, ETL, data engineering
- Cloud: GCP, gcloud CLI, AWS, AWS CLI, Docker, Kubernetes